[
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "The delta of the River Nile is best described as",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "bird's foot",
            "estuarine",
            "arcuate",
            "lacustrine",
            "cuspate"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Which of the following soils is easily water-logged?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Alluvial soil",
            "Sandy soil",
            "Clayey soil",
            "Loamy soil",
            "Lateritic soil"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "The green plants which serve as producer to other organisms in the ecosystem are called",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "autotrophs",
            "heterotrophs",
            "decomposers",
            "biota",
            "components"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "A major characteristic of the tropical woodland vegetation is that",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "it consists of grass and shrubs only",
            "the forest consists of scattered trees only",
            "it consists mainly of mangroves",
            "the forest it too closely spaced to permit any undergrowth",
            "its open forest permits the growth of grass"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "The Westerlies and the North-East Trade Winds are similar because they both",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "originate from the Horse Latitudes of the northern hemisphere",
            "blow towards the temperate low pressure belt of the northen hemisphere",
            "converge at the doldrums in summer",
            "carry moisture to the coasts of Europe in summer",
            "blow towards the Horse Latitudes"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Visibility usually decreases when a",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "cold, dry wind blows over a cold current",
            "body of fresh water mingles with salty water",
            "warm wind blows over a warm current",
            "warm dry wind rises over a high mountain",
            "warm current meets a cold current"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Diurnal range of temperature is the difference between the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "highest and the lowest temperature recorded in a station every year",
            "highest and the lowest temperature recorded in a station everyday",
            "highest and the lowest temperatures recorded in a station every month",
            "readings of the wet bulb and the dry bulb thermometers",
            "maximum and the minium temperatures at any time of the year"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "They are tropical and subtropical storms, occurring over land, they are funnel-shaped and violent, with winds of high velocity reaching up to 330kmph, which of the following winds is described above?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "Chinook",
            "Hurricane",
            "Typhoon",
            "Fohn",
            "Tornado"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Which of the following least influences the growth of settlements?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Age",
            "Climate",
            "Mineral resources",
            "Relief",
            "Manufacturing industries"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "which of the following is a disadvantage of water transport?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "causes atmospheric pollution",
            "is used for carrying agricultural commodities only",
            "is not flexible",
            "is not suitable for international trade",
            "cannot carry bulky goods"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "One important consequence of the location of Nigeria between latitudes 4<sup>0</sup>and 14<sup>0</sup>North of the equator is that",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "some parts of the country enjoy a hot, wet, tropical climate throughout the year",
            "the south westerly winds blow only across the coastal areas",
            "all parts of country receive rainfall throughout the year",
            "all part of the country have a luxuriant vegetation",
            "the northern part of the country enjoys land sea breezes"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "A specialized mode of transportation used in carrying coal from Enugu to Oji River is the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "pipeline",
            "transmission line",
            "rope way",
            "rail cart",
            "jumbo plane"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Which of the geographical regions of Nigeria contains volcanic plugs, inselbergs and crater lake?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Eastern scarplands",
            "Western highlands",
            "North-central highland",
            "Eastern highlands",
            "Chad Basin"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "The location of the oil refinery at Kaduna is best explained by the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "deliberate government policy and market",
            "presence of power supply and market",
            "availability of raw material and capital",
            "adequate transportation and labour",
            "presence of raw material and government policy"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "All the following statements are true of the savanna vegetation in Nigeria except that the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "trees are deciduous",
            "trees have thick water-storing trunks",
            "trees have long tap root systems",
            "grasses are tall and luxuriant in the wet season",
            "trees occur in the pure stands"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "A major characteristic of local craft industry is that",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "it requires a specially built factory",
            "it is mainly hereditry",
            "it requires a large labour force",
            "its products are used by other industries",
            "its raw materials are imported"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "In Africa coral reef coasts are largely located in the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "north-west",
            "sourth-west",
            "west",
            "south",
            "south-east"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Which of the following vegetation types is most common in Africa?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Steppe",
            "Campos",
            "Selvas",
            "Savanna",
            "Prairies"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "In Africa, the veldt is located in the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "western coastland",
            "eastern coastland",
            "continental interior",
            "extreme north and south",
            "southern part"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Africa has the largest potential reserves of hydro-electric power in the world due to",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "its many plateaus",
            "its high demand for power",
            "the abundant rainfall and waterfalls there",
            "the presence of very long rivers",
            "the high growth of industrial development"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "The low level of trade among West African countries is mainly because",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "of mistrust among them",
            "of the language barrier",
            "there is a well developed transport network",
            "they produce similar goods",
            "they have different currencies"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "The basin system of irrigation in the Nile Basin is not reliable because",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "too much of the water percolates into the ground",
            "only a few crops can be grown",
            "it is not considered suitable by some farmers",
            "too much labour is involved in making the basins",
            "it depends on the flow of the Nile in a particular year"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Which of the following represents the first stage in the lumbering process?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Trees are felled",
            "Platforms are built for buttress trees",
            "Particular species are identified",
            "Trees are cut into logs",
            "Logs are transported by road to sawmills"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "The Muturu type of cattle is reared mainly in the western highland region of Nigeria because",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "it has no hump",
            "of the harsh weather of the North-central highlands",
            "it is resistant to tsetse files",
            "of the luxuriant pasture there",
            "it produces a lot of milk"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Monoculture is a term associated with",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "livestock farming",
            "arable farming",
            "mixed farming",
            "plantation agriculture",
            "shifting cultivation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 1996,
        "question": "Some plant diseases are checked during the fallow periods in the bush fallowing system of agriculture because the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "humus accumulates over time",
            "fires used in clearing the bush destroy them",
            "plant species resist the diseases",
            "disease organisms lose their hosts and die",
            "land is heavily fragmented"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    }
]